Finding Aid for Ann Arbor, Michigan photograph collection 1860s-1970s
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor, Michigan photograph collection
1860s-1970s
Bentley Historical Library (collector)
Photographs collected from various donors relating to Ann Arbor, Michigan; include photos of buildings (public and private), houses, churches, and schools; also views of the city (by street and area); and miscellaneous photos of local events and activities, school class portraits, and other group portraits.
91153 UCCs UCCm
2 linear feet UCCs
2 oversize folders UCCm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was assembled by Michigan Historical Collections staff over a period of years from a variety of sources and donors.
The collection is open for research. Some photos from the collection are available on-line through the world wide web as part of the Bentley Library's Image Bank. Links to the digitized images are provided in the container listing.
The Ann Arbor, Michigan Photographs Collection was assembled by the staff of the Bentley Historical Library.
This collection of Ann Arbor photographs includes a wide variety of images of Ann Arbor buildings, street scenes, schools and classrooms, public events, and people. The images, dating from the 1860s to the 1970s, has been arranged into three series: Buildings, Houses, etc.; Views; and Activities, People, Events. Each folder may contain one or more images.
The researcher should be advised that this collection represents only a small portion of the library's Ann Arbor photos. The most complete access to the total holdings of the library is through the card catalog.
Subjects - Visual Materials
African Americans.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Panoramic views.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Schools.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Ann Arbor Street Railway Company.; Ann Arbor Taxicab Co. (Ann Arbor, Mich.)--Employees.Employees.; Ann Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Argo Mills (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Bach & Abel (Dry goods store: Ann Arbor, Mich.); Bach School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Baseball players--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Bryant School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Cemeteries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor Central Mills (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; City and town halls--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; City Ice Company (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Courthouses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dixboro School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Donovan School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Dr. Chase's Steam Printing House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Eberbach School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Eberwhite School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Fire engines and equipment.; Fire stations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Fires--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Baptist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); First Congregational Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); First Methodist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); First Unitarian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Forest Hill Cemetery (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Frieze Building (University of Michigan); German Americans.; Bethlehem Evangelical Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Goodyear & St. James Drygoods Store (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Gregory House (Hotel: Ann Arbor, Mich.); Huron Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Jones School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor.; Lower Town (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Mack & Company (Ann Arbor, Mich.)--Fire.Fire.; Mack School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Main Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Majestic Theatre (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Masonic Temple (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Maynard Store (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Memorial Christian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Michigan Central Railroad Depot (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Northwest School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Perry School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Pioneer High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Political parades and rallies.; Porter Zouave Band (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Post offices--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Railroad bridges--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Railroad stations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Residential streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Slauson Junior High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Tappan Junior High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Telephone--Employees.; Toll roads--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; Washtenaw County Courthouse (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Young Men's Christian Association (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Aerial photographs.; Panoramic views.; Photographs.; Stereographs.
- Ann Arbor Photographs
  - Buildings, Houses, etc.
    The Buildings series has four subseries. The first - Buildings" - consists of photos of the exterior of Ann Arbor businesses and other public buildings (such as the post office and the engine house of the fire department).
    The second subseries consists of photographs (primarily exterior views) of Ann Arbor churches. The third subseries includes photos of Ann Arbor houses, arranged alphabetically by owner's name or by the street location if the owner's name is not clear. The last subseries contains photos of various Ann Arbor schools.
    - Buildings
      - Argo Mills Milling Co. (Folder 1)
      - Bach & Abel dry goods store (Folder 2)
      - Bank building (lower Town) (Folder 3)
      - Central Mills (Folder 4)
      - Chase's (Dr.) Steam Printing House (Folder 5)
      - City Hall (construction views), 1962 (Folder 6)
      - City Ice Company (Folder 7)
      - Court Houses (Folder 8)
      - Fire Department Engine Houses (Folder 9)
        (also photos of horse-drawn engines leaving building)
      - Forest Hill Cemetery (Folder 10)
      - Goodyear & St. James (Folder 11)
      - Gregory House (Folder 12)
      - Ladies Library Association (Folder 13)
      - Majestic Theater (Folder 14)
      - Masonic Temple, circa 1920s (Folder 15)
      - Maynard Store (Folder 16)
      - Michigan Central Depot (Folder 17)
      - Muehlig's (Folder 18)
        (store window display of historical memorabilia)
      - Post Office (Folder 19)
        (include stereoscope cards)
      - YMCA (old) building (Folder 29)
      - Unidentified (Ann St. at 4th Ave.) (Folder 21)
    - Churches (by denomination)
      - Baptist (Folder 22)
      - Church of Christ (Memorial), 1923 (Folder 23)
        (includes interiors and views along South University)
      - Congregational (Folder 24)
        (include stereoscope card)
      - Episcopal (St. Andrew's) (Folder 25)
      - Methodist (Folder 27)
        (includes stereoscope cards)
      - Presbyterian (Folder 28)
        (includes stereoscope card)
      - Presbyterian (Folder UCCm)
      - Unitarian (old), later became Grace Bible Church (Folder 29)
    - Houses
      - Ann Arbor and Saline Plank Road House (S. Main) (Folder 30)
      - Beckley House (Pontiac Trail) (Folder 31)
      - Brown House (Hill Street) (Folder 32)
      - Cooley (Charles Horton) House (Folder 33)
      - Cooley (Thomas) House (Folder 34)
      - D'Ooge House (Washtenaw) (Folder 35)
      - Foster (James) House (Folder 36)
      - Herbst House (Washtenaw) (Folder 37)
      - James (Enoch) House (E. Liberty) (Folder 38)
      - Jefferson St. House (Folder 39)
      - Martin House (Miller Road) (Folder 40)
      - Millen House (also Phi Kappa Psi house) (Folder 41)
      - Pond (Elihu) House (Folder 42)
      - Porter House (Washtenaw) also Langley & Hinsdale House (Folder 43)
      - State Street Houses (Folder 44)
      - Winchell House (Folder 45)
      - Unidentified (Folder 46)
    - Schools
      - Dixboro (Folder 47)
      - Eberbach (Folder 48)
      - High School
        - Union High School (Folder 49)
        - Frieze Building (Folder 50)
          (includes science lab?)
        - Pioneer High School (Folder 51)
      - Jones (Folder 52)
      - Mack (Folder 53)
      - Northwest (now Haisley) (Folder 54)
      - Slauson Junior High School (Folder 55)
      - Tappan (Folder 56)
  - Ann Arbor Views
    The Views series has two subseries: by street, and by area. Where the Buildings series generally included photos of a single building, the Views series usually contains views along a street, at an intersection, or taken from an elevated location (such as aerial views or photos taken from the courthouse roof).
    - By Street
      - Ann (Folder 57)
      - Huron, 2 envelopes
        - Huron (Folder 58)
        - Huron (Folder 59)
          (continued)
      - Main Street (Folder 60)
      - State Street (Folder 61)
      - Various (Folder 62)
    - By Area
      - Lower Town and Mills (Folder 63)
      - Michigan Central Railroad depot area and related (Folder 64)
      - Taken from the Boulevard (NE) (Folder 65)
      - Taken from the Courthouse Tower (Folder 66)
      - Taken from the West (Sunset Hill) (Folder 67)
      - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Folder 68)
  - Activities, Events, People
    The series Activities, People, Events - is a miscellaneous collection of photos relating to Ann Arbor life. It includes group photos, and photos of fires, historical gatherings, and school classrooms.
    - Ann Arbor City Officials, 1909 (Folder 69)
    - Ann Arbor Taxicab Co. banquet, 1916 (Folder 70)
    - Barton Hills party, 1920 (Folder 71)
    - Civil War gathering (Folder 72)
      (gathering in downtown area with news of outbreak of war)
    - Fire engine (horse-drawn) on route to fire (Folder 73)
    - Mack & Company fire, 1899 (Folder 74)
    - Porter Zouave band members (Folder 75)
    - Schools (mainly class portraits or pupils in class)
      - Bach (Folder 76)
      - Bryant (Folder 77)
      - Donovan (and unidentified), 1911 (Folder 78)
      - Eberbach (Folder 79)
      - Eberwhite (Folder 80)
      - High School (Folder 81)
      - High School (Folder UCCm)
      - Jones (Folder 82)
      - Mack (Folder 83)
      - Perry (Folder 84)
      - Tappan (Folder 85)
    - Superior Dairy baseball team, 1911 (Folder UCCm)
    - Telephone anniversary gathering, 1926 (Folder 86)
    - Transportation (includes street cars, carts, etc.) (Folder 87)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Folder 88)
      (includes visit of Marshall Foch to Ann Arbor in 1921)
- Ann Arbor Prints
  - Buildings Houses etc
    - William S. Maynard residence, R.A. Beal residence corner of 5th and William, Stebbins and Wilson Store